<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the birth of God in all the sanctified, the church of the first-born, whose names are written in heaven who are born again, not of the will of the flesh, but of God's Holy Spirit: you to whom is given the white stone, and the new name, that none knows but he that hath it, who as living stones are laid in the walls (not of the Jerusalem that now is, and is in bondage with her children, but) of the new Jerusalem that is above, (in the heart and throne of God) which is free, and is the mother of us all. To you, however you are divided, or where-ever ye are lodg'd, and held in the clifts of the rocks, in Dens and caves of the earth, or secret places of the stars; under all your divided tribes, Robert Rich sendeth greeting in our Lord God everlasting. Allelujah.</title>
            <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57219</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833337</idno>
  <idno type="VID">37813</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240955376</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1364</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222107</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833337</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99833337e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37813)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2196:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the birth of God in all the sanctified, the church of the first-born, whose names are written in heaven who are born again, not of the will of the flesh, but of God's Holy Spirit: you to whom is given the white stone, and the new name, that none knows but he that hath it, who as living stones are laid in the walls (not of the Jerusalem that now is, and is in bondage with her children, but) of the new Jerusalem that is above, (in the heart and throne of God) which is free, and is the mother of us all. To you, however you are divided, or where-ever ye are lodg'd, and held in the clifts of the rocks, in Dens and caves of the earth, or secret places of the stars; under all your divided tribes, Robert Rich sendeth greeting in our Lord God everlasting. Allelujah.</title>
                  <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1680.]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends' House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37813:1"/>
            <head>To the Birth of God in all the Sanctified, the <hi>Church of the First-Born,</hi> whose Names are written in Heaven; who are born again, not of the Will of the Flesh, but of God's Holy Spirit: You to whom is given the White Stone, and the New Name, that none knows but he that hath it, who as living Stones are laid in the Walls (not of the <hi>Jerusalem</hi> that now is, and is in bondage with her Children, but) of the <hi>New Jerusalem</hi> that is Above, (in the Heart and Throne of God) which is Free, and is the Mother of us all. To you, however you are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, or where-ever ye are lodg'd, and held in the Clifts of the Rocks, in Dens and Caves of the Earth, or secret places of the Stars; under all your divided Tribes, <hi>RO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT RICH</hi> sendeth Greeting in our Lord God Everlasting. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing moved in my Spirit, in the Year 1666, to sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lute the Seed of God, the Seed of the Promise in all Men, and in particular the <hi>Seven Churches</hi> of <hi>Christendom;</hi> namely, the <hi>Roman;</hi> the <hi>Episcopal Protestant;</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian;</hi> the <hi>Independent;</hi> the <hi>Baptist;</hi> the <hi>Quaker;</hi> and the <hi>Church of the First-Born;</hi> to each of them I gave <hi>Thirty pounds,</hi> to be distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted amongst the Poor of their People, as a sign of my dear Love to the Seed of God in all, which I saw lay crucified, dead and buried in some, and in others risen and reigning into Life
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37813:2"/>that is Eternal. That which principally moved me to this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Salutation, was, the sad and serious apprehension of the Straits and Limits by which I saw the Seed of God held in Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and these several sorts of Professors to value themselves, and also condemn one another, in reference to those Modes and Methods of Worship and Obedience, in which they are divided and distinguished. My Salutation intended a check to this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind severity amongst them; and according to the inward Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony from God upon my Spirit (if possible) to let them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, that our gracious God is no respecter of Persons, Sects, or Opinions, but of every Nation, those that fear God and work Righteousness, are accepted of him; and that all those that walk in the Light of the Lord, wherewith he hath enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them, are saved. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Heavenly Revelation of this Blessed Vision, wherein I felt and found my self in a through Reconcilement to all Sorts and Sects of Men, I have begun, and now finished my <hi>Epistles</hi> to these <hi>Seven States of Christians,</hi> which I recommend to the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light,</hi> to read and to consider what the Spirit saith to the <hi>Churches.</hi> And because in the Travels of this Testimony up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Soul, I have met with several Celestial Pilgrims journying towards <hi>Sion,</hi> with their Faces thitherward, by whose sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, in many of their Books and Papers, I have bin often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed and comforted: I cannot but commend, both their Names and Labours, to the sober Enquirers after Truth; as well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that though these Witnesses are dead and gone, yet their Spirits and Testimony remain, and still speak to us. At this time I read many Books writ by the Divine Spirit, in which I took great delight, some few whereof I find freedom to expa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate on.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Cebes</hi> the <hi>Theban</hi> Philosopher, his Table writ in <hi>Greek,</hi> (since translated into <hi>English</hi>) who lived <hi>Anno Mundi</hi> 3553; which Table was hung up in the Temple of <hi>Saturn.</hi> This Table consisted of three Parks or Inclosures; at the Gate of the first stood the shape of an Old Man, called <hi>Life's Genius,</hi> (afterwards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37813:2"/>
               <hi>True Instruction</hi>) which I understand by interpretation, to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent the Light and Grace of God, which appeareth to and in every one. This Light, or <hi>Life's Genius,</hi> taught and instructed all how they should lead their Lives, according to those Rules he directed, both to avoid temptations to Vice, and to imbrace all those Divine Vertues that lead to Beatitude.</p>
            <p>I have read the <hi>Imitation of Christ,</hi> writ by <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Kempis.</hi> Also Cardinal <hi>Cusanus,</hi> his first, second, and third <hi>Rule of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> and his <hi>Idiot;</hi> with others of the like Divine Nature, all tending to a Holy Life, by virtue of Christ's Holy Spirit in us, the only way to Life and Salvation. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have also read many Divine Works writ by <hi>H. N. Jacob Behm, John Saltmarsh,</hi> Dr. <hi>Everard, William Sedgwick, William Erbery,</hi> Dr. <hi>Gill,</hi> Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> with others that were inspired of God, and spake of the second Coming of Christ in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and of that blessed Day which should attend his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have also read, with much delight, two Books writ by <hi>J. N.</hi> called, <hi>Love to the Lost,</hi> and, <hi>A Salutation to the Seed of God in all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Also one small Book writ by <hi>John Perrot,</hi> entituled, <hi>An Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle for the most pure Amity and Ʋnity in the Spirit and Life of God, to all sincere-hearted Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have likewise lately read some Prophecies and Predictions of that Holy Learned Man <hi>James Ʋsher,</hi> Lord Arch-Bishop of <hi>Armagh;</hi> who through Inspiration of God's Spirit, spake of many things which long after came to pass: that which is to me most remarkable in that Sheet of Paper is, that he being intreated to write in brief of <hi>Justification</hi> and <hi>Sanctification,</hi> desired he might be excused; notwithstanding the Person soliciting, through importunity, obtained a promise: A while after his Promise be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing claimed, he replied, <q>He had not writ, yet could not charge himself with breach of Promise, for <hi>(said he)</hi> I did begin to write, but when I came to write of <hi>Sanctification,</hi> that is, of the New Creature which God formeth by his Spirit in every
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37813:3"/>Soul which he doth truly regenerate, I found so little wrought of it in my self, that I could speak of it, only as a Parrot by rote, without knowledg and understanding, and therefore durst not proceed any further upon it. <hi>Adding,</hi> I must tell you, we do not well understand what <hi>Sanctification</hi> and the <hi>New Birth</hi> is; It is no less than for a Man to be brought to an entire Resignation of his own Will to the Will of God, and to live in the offering up of his Soul continually in the flames of Love, as a holy burnt Offering to Christ. And how little <hi>(says he)</hi> are many of those that profess Christianity, experimentally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with this Work of Regeneration in their Souls? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he desires his Friend to look he be not found a Worshipper in the outward Court; which outward Court <hi>(says he)</hi> is the formal Christian, whose Religion lies in performing the out-side Duties of Christianity, without having an inward Life and Power of Faith and Love uniting them to Christ; and these God will leave to be trodden down and swept away by the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> the Prophane that call themselves <hi>Christians,</hi> but are the Synagogue of <hi>Satan.</hi> The Worshippers within the Temple, and before the Altar, are those that do worship God in Spirit and in Truth, whose Souls are made his Temples, and he is honoured and adored in the most inward Thoughts of their Hearts; and they Sacrifice their Lusts and vile Affections, yea, and their own Wills to him, and these God will hide in the hollow of his Hand, and under the shadow of his Wings, and shall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served as a Seed, to partake of that Glory which shall immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately follow.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I have also lately read two Treatises writ by Sir <hi>Henry Vane;</hi> First, <hi>An Epistle General to the Mystical Body of Christ on Earth, the Church Ʋniversal in Babylon.</hi> The second, <hi>The Face of the Times.</hi> Wherein he well discovers the Rise, Progress, and Issue, of the Enmity and Contest between the Seed of the Woman, and the Seed of the Serpent. He saith, <q>That till the Seventh Trump sound, 1666, the Woman's Seed must suffer; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Seed of the Woman being risen with Christ, must
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37813:3"/>reign with him; and then the Head of the Serpent should be bruised.</q> He speaketh most excellently of the first and second Covenant, and of a single and double Portion of the Spirit, of Regeneration and Restoration into the first Estate in <hi>Paradise,</hi> which may fall; also of the New Creation, or Second Birth, (the Seed of God in Man) which endures, and never will, nor ever can fall. <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He saith, <q>The <hi>Quakers</hi> Principle is, To restore out of the Fall into the first State, who though they are Angels, yet may fall. He shews how Angels fell, who through pride oppose all higher Lights than themselves, and that such fallen Angels be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the greatest Enemies to the Birth of Christ in the Saints; which Spirit is the great Antichrist, the Old Serpent, the Devil, that is to be cast into the Bottomless-Pit, with all his Angels; who outwardly appear as Angels of Light, but inwardly they devour the Innocent.</q> This I have seen to be a Truth, in the bitter contests betwixt <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Angels, and the self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, humble, meek Spirit that was in <hi>J. N.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> and those that suffered with them, for bearing their Testimony to Christ in the Saints, which is the last, the most glorious and highest Dispensation (<hi>as saith Sir</hi> H. V.) now at the very Doors; a Truth which many can Witness. <hi>He further saith,</hi>
               <q>The Lamb will overcome by Sufferings; and that the first sign of Christ's second Coming, is distress of Nations; that the Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sherds of the Earth dashing one against the other, will make way for Christ's Reign; in which War, none but Hypocrites and Apostates (which make the outward Court) will suffer, whilst God's People will be preserved in Peace and Safety.</q>
               <hi>Sir</hi> H. V. <hi>also saith,</hi>
               <q>The Holy City and Temple measured, are Saints in Power: That the Woman clothed with the Sun, is Christ's dead Body raised. <hi>Ʋrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim, (he saith)</hi> are the two great Lights, <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> when they meet in our Hearts. It is <hi>(he saith)</hi> a fickle and foolish Religion, that depends on the Magistrates Power, either to set up or pull down. That Believers Rewards in Sufferings, is inward Peace
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37813:4"/>and Joy in a serene quiet Mind.</q> He was also in his day a great Prophet, <hi>(he saith)</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Israel</hi>'s Captivity is near an end, at which time the Sons of God shall be made manifest; so soon as that is come, there will need little other help than the Grave it self to cast them forth, as the Womb doth the Fruit; then shall you know the Lord is God when he hath opened and brought you up out of your Graves; such will the Lord own visibly for his People, by putting his wonderful Spirit in them, and then will God's Indignation be poured out upon his Enemies. That the Nation that hath kept the Seed of God in Bondage, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self God will judg more signally than he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> in this day shall the Tabernacle of God in Men be visible. <hi>He also saith,</hi> Doubtless great and precious Promises are to be accomplished in and upon Believers here on Earth, to the making of Christ admired in them. That this dark Night and black Shade, that God hath drawn over his work in the midst of us, may be the Ground Colour to some beautiful Piece that he is now exposing to the light. That surely God hath a glorious Design to carry on in the World, even the building of <hi>David</hi>'s Throne to all Generations. I know a Day of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for <hi>Sion</hi> will come, not with confused noise of the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier, and Garments rouling in Blood, but with burning and fuel of Fire in the Consciences of Men. Men they may fight against, but this they can never fight against. The Day approaches wherein God will decide his Controversy with the World, not by outward Might and Power, but by the Spirit of the Living God. <hi>'Twas an usual saying with him,</hi> Come what would, every thing was upon the right Wheel, in the wise contrivement of God, for the accomplishing of his Righteous Designs in the World.</q>
               <hi>And speaking to his Children, saith,</hi>
               <q>Regard not the Reproaches that are fallen on your Father, say, or do Men what they will, <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith will find the Blessing <hi>Abraham</hi> found.</q> These, and many more of His, as of Others, I take to be true and faithful Sayings, meet to be considered by all that wait for, and expect Redemption, Consolation, and Salvation from the God of <hi>Israel. Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37813:4"/>
            <p> You will not blame me, that I have enlarged upon the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of these Holy Men, that have finished their Course, kept the Faith, and are gone before us into the Eternal Mansions of Glory; who having quitted their Mortal Fabricks, are flown into the World of hidden Wonders. The Spirits of these Just Men made perfect, are now upon you, ye are come up to them, and in the harmonious Fellowship of that Spirit, (which is now one and the same amongst all the Sanctified,) I have a few words of my inward Breathings to communicate to your holy Experiences.</p>
            <p>In a deep sense thereof, of my endeared Love towards that Royal Seed that richly dwells in you, I here salute you, and give you to understand, That my Soul is firmly knit and united to that Principle of Life in which you stand, bearing your Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimony for the Truth, before God and Man, amongst a crooked and perverse Generation; who only dwell upon the out-side talks and pretences to God, Religion and Christianity, but hate even to Blood and Violence, all those that are the free-born Seed of the Promise; whose Faith and Obedience stands not in the Will, Work, or Wisdom of Man, but in the Power and Spirit of God, mightily working in their Hearts and Consciences, whereby they are indeed purified, washed, and cleansed from dead Works to serve the Living God. And so much the more is my Heart inflamed towards you, when I consider you in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</p>
            <p>First, To the Nature of your present Station.</p>
            <p>And secondly, To those great Designs that God hath prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you for.</p>
            <p>First, For the Nature of your present Station, I behold you (not as <hi>Moab, Jer.</hi> 48.11, 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but) as a People standing in a more inward nearness with God, than the rest of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Tribes of Religious Proselytes in the World; a People that have bin scattered from all your fleshly Comforts and Confidences in all those Joys, Hopes, Helps, and Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherein you have trusted, below God. You have bin
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37813:5"/>led into the Deeps of God's Wonders, while others have bin only wading in the shallow Streams of a literal and formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession: Unto you it is given to know those Mysteries of the Kingdom of God, which lie hid from others in dark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scure Parables; you know that the Son of God is come, and hath given you an understanding to know him that is True, and that ye are in Him that is True, which is the very God and Eternal Life. You cannot be deceived with the tinkling Noises, or glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Baits of, <hi>Loe here,</hi> or <hi>Loe there,</hi> for the Kingdom of God is within you. In a word, there is nothing below Spirit, Power, and Substance, that can either crown your longing Expectations, or reward your holy Breathings after Truth, with a plenary and full satisfaction. Thus as the Lord's Lillies among Thorns, so do you stand among the formal Daughters, being preserved in your Station, upheld in your Principles, and as Beacons flaming with the holy Blazes of a free and universal Love, serve to enlighten the World into the way of Truth, and direct their Feet into the Paths of that Peace, Amity, Union, Rest, and Security, to which as yet they are so much estranged.</p>
            <p>And this leads me to the other Consideration of the Great Work, and High Designs which God hath prepared you for. And surely glorious Things are spoken of thee, O thou City of God! You are not only as Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> beautiful for Scituation, but also the Joy of the whole Earth, for those humble, gentle, lovely, and pleasant Aspects, by which you shine upon the whole World, with the inviting and astonishing Charms of a divinely inspired Love and Affection; You are a People fitted above all others to be a Blessing to the World; the whole Creation seems to groan and travel in pain, with a longing and languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expectation to be delivered into the glorious Liberty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ye stand. O how hath the form and out-side of Religion, (mixed with Carnal Interest) exposed the World to Extremities of Horror and Confusion, as at this day? What indignity and reproach doth indelebly stick upon the Skirts of Profession and Christianity, through that fiery and mis-guided Zeal, those Feuds
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37813:5"/>and bitter Animosities, that Strife and Debate, that Blood and Violence which abounds amongst those that walk under the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Names of Gospel-Professors and True Christians? How in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sipid, lifeless, and unsavory is the whole state of formal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession grown, who while they cry up a Christ that died for them, and contend for an Historical Faith of his Death and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, hoping to be saved by a bare Imputation of a Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness wrought without them, and yet know nothing all this while of any inward change, or renewedness of Mind and Heart; but totally ignorant of the inward active and real Righteousness, which should commend them to the World in an healing, saving, comforting, and refreshing Spirit? And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the higher People are advanced in a literal and carnal Knowledg of God and Christ, the more rough, bitter, and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere will their temper be towards all others that differ from them in the least Circumstances of Religion, it being natural to that Knowledg and Wisdom, to swell and puff up the Mind in the lofty and high conceits of a self-Righteousness, rather than sweeten and soften the Spirit in that Charity which edifies. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, this is the distracted Station wherein the Children of Form are truly presented (as <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s lean Kine) tearing and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring each other in this day of Wrath: for now is the Judgment of this World; and what may quench these Flames? what may quel these Disorders? what may repair these Breaches, or allay these Distempers, is the main thing that would be most desirable to know?</p>
            <p>We see that neither the Prudence of Princes, nor the Policies of Government (the Prescriptions of the wisest Reformers, nor the best esteemed Regularities of the most magnified Authors, and reverend Fathers) are capable to accomplish this Reconciling Work: Nay, the Sacred Oracle of the Scripture it self, is so far short of obtaining this blessed End, that all different Parties do endeavour, with the greatest industry imaginable, (by warping and winding the Text) not only to suit it to the occasion of their present Differences, but also thereby to justify their mad,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37813:6"/>blind, and uncharitable Zeal towards each other: What Remedy then is left us in this Distress? Is there no Balm in <hi>Gilead?</hi> Yes certainly, for although the extent of our Wounds and Breaches are too wide and great for the most ample Wisdom and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousness of Man to heal and cement, there is yet largeness enough in the eternal and universal Love of God to accomplish this great Work, and to make his <hi>Jerusalem</hi> a Praise upon the Earth: And 'tis (my dear Brethren) by the ample and large manifesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this Universal Love, shed abroad in your Hearts, that this great Design of God must be accomplished; and oh how the Consideration of this Glorious Work, (in and by you to be brought forth) doth draw out my Spirit towards you. <hi>Awake, awake then, put on thy strength, O Sion, put on thy beautiful Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, O</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>thou Holy City; stand forth thou Virgin Daughter, clothed with the strength of the Divine Majesty, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Glory of your Principles, by the beauty of your Practices to the World.</hi> There is Majesty enough in that Love which fills and feeds your Souls, to confound the Cruelty of all your Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posers, to shame and astonish the World into silence and stilness; and of this let us be confident, that how-ever the over-flowing Tides of common Calamities (blown up by the raging breath of formal and carnal Interests) may swell as a Flood upon the World, yet no Weapon that is form'd against Love (to Truth and Righteousness) shall prosper; the <hi>Heathen</hi> may rage, and the People may imagine a vain Thing: The Kings of the Earth may Plot, Conspire, and take Counsel together against the Lord, and against his Anointed; yet the Lord hath set his King upon his Holy Hill of <hi>Zion,</hi> and he shall and doth Rule and Reign in the midst of his Enemies: Let it therefore appear to the World, whose Subjects ye are, whose Banner ye are under and what Motto it bears, which is, <hi>Glory to God in the Highest, on Earth Peace, and good Will towards Men.</hi> O how beautiful will those feet be upon the Mountains, which are shod with the preparation of the Gospel of Peace; <hi>How beautiful are thy Feet with Shooes, O Princes Daughter?</hi> Cant. 7.1. How amiable and pleasant will
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37813:6"/>your Lives and Testimonies be among Men, when you come forth in the largeness of that Love, Meekness, and Humility, in Forbearance and Forgiveness, which are the proper Ornaments, and most natural Instances of a true Gospel-Profession? In the Name of God arise then, and shew your selves (in his strength) to be that in Power and Life, which the World are only in Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and Notion; let it be known by the lively and active de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrations of the Spirit of God in you, <hi>That greater is He that is in you, than he that is in the World:</hi> Your Principles I am sure are more noble, extensive, and generous; do but draw them forth, and shew them to open view, and you will be a Blessing in your Generation; The several Tribes and Languages shall fasten on your Skirts, and say, <hi>We will go along with you, for the Lord is amongst you:</hi> Nay, even the <hi>Kings of the Nations shall shut their Mouths at this appearance of God in you,</hi> Isa. 52.14, 15. <hi>For that which had not bin told them, they shall see, and that which they had not heard, they shall consider.</hi> (As <hi>Pharaoh</hi> said of <hi>Joseph, Where is there a Man in whom the Spirit of God is? Gen.</hi> 41.38, &amp;c.) Finally, my Brethren, <hi>Be strong in the Lord, and in the Power of his Might; put on the whole Armour of God, for your Work and your Warfare requires it;</hi> and ye know that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing below that can enable you to finish this your Testimony: <hi>Ye wrestle not against Flesh and Blood; neither are the Weapons of your Warfare Carnal, but mighty through God, to subdue every high Thought, and vain Imagination.</hi> All those Principalities and Powers, and those spiritual Wickednesses in high Places, which have captivated the Royal Seed of the Promise, and exalted themselves against the free Breathings of the Spirit; These (my dear Friends) are the powerful Enemies, over which ye must be more than Conquerors through him that loves you; and when in the strength of this Love you have subdued the World, calm'd and quieted that wild and furious Spirit of Wrath that is let loose among Men, and prepared the way for the Kingdom of God, and of his Christ, to be establish'd in us, and amongst us; what remains, but that in a holy denial of your Selves and Services,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37813:7"/>(your Gifts and Graces, your Love and Enlargements, your Faith and Patience, your Sufferings and Perseverances) you offer up the Son of the Promise, and cast down these your Crowns at the feet of Him that sits upon the Throne, joining in Consort with the Celestial Quire of Saints and Angels in the Sacred Hymns of Divine Praises, and <hi>Allelujahs; Salvation, and Glory, and Honour, and Power, to the Lord our God,</hi> (Rev. 19.1, to 10.) <hi>Not unto us Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name, be the glory of all thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous Works.</hi> Sing <hi>Zion,</hi> shout O ye Inhabitants of the <hi>New Jerusalem.</hi> Judges 5.1, to 14. <hi>Awake</hi> Deborah, <hi>awake, awake, sing to the Lord; Arise</hi> Barak, take the Harps of God in your hands, ye Heavenly Victors; and in your most strenuous Notes, sing aloud with <hi>Moses</hi> and the Lamb upon your Chrystal fiery Floods: Rev. 15.2, 3, 4. <hi>Great and marvellous are thy Works, Lord God Almighty; Just and true are thy Ways, thou King of Saints, who will not fear thee, O God, and glorify thy Name? for thou only art Holy; all Nations shall come and worship before thee, for thy Judgments are made manifest.</hi> And again, <hi>Allelujah, for the Lord God Omnipotent reigneth, and is manifest to be All in All, all Ʋnity in all Variety.</hi> Thus to ascribe to God All in all, and to the Creature-Nothing, is the top-Stone of God's Building, to which we cry, <hi>Grace, Grace. Allelujah.</hi> For His is the Kingdom, the Power and the Glory, for ever and ever. <hi>Amen. Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>